Guide to the Evans Family Papers, 1920s-1990s RL.00369
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Evans family papers
1920s-1990s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00369
24 Linear Feet 5609 Items
Collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, albums, clippings, addresses, writings, and other materials that concern the personal lives and careers of Mr. and Mrs. Emanuel J. ("Mutt") and Sara Evans, and their sons, Robert and Eli. Mutt Evans's mayoral correspondence is divided into a general file and a subject file. Some materials depict the private lives of the Evanses, including photographs, albums, and personal correspondence. Sara's family, the Nachamsons, is often represented. The collection also includes extensive documentation about Sara's role in Hadassah, both locally and nationally, as well as the family's participation in other Isareli and Jewish causes. Also included are materials from their work in developing and fundraising for the Judaic Studies Program at Duke University.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Evans Family papers were a gift to Duke University in 1986 and 1989.
Biographical Note
The Evans family was active in Durham, N.C. civic leadership, local and national Jewish leadership, and national journalism. The family owned and operated United Dollar stores, and for twelve years, 1951 to 1963, E.J. "Mutt" Evans was mayor of Durham. Mutt Evans was a president of VISTAS, and participated actively in University of North Carolina alumni affairs. Sara Evans was a leader at both the local and national levels of Hadassah. The couple was also very active in their synagogue, Beth El. Both sons attended the University of North Carolina and were student leaders on campus. Robert Evans became a correspondent with CBS, working with Edward R. Murrow, and then a television executive. Eli Evans is a correspondent and writer, led the establishment of the National Jewish Archives of Broadcasting, and was on the staff of the Carnegie Foundation that helped launch "Sesame Street." He also authored THE PROVINCIALS and JUDAH P. BENJAMIN: THE JEWISH CONFEDERATE, and serves as president of the Charles H. Revson Foundation.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks, albums, clippings, addresses, writings, and other materials that concern the personal lives and careers of the Evans family, particularly Emanuel J. and Sara Evans, their sons, Eli and Robert, and Emanuel's brother, Monroe. The family owned and operated United Department Stores, and for twelve years, 1951 to 1963, Emanuel Evans was mayor of Durham, NC. He was also very active in his synagogue, was a president of VISTAS, and participated actively in the University of North Carolina's Alumni Association.
There are two scrapbooks on Emanuel Evans's mayoral terms and a similar volume and other materials devoted to Mrs. Evans's activities as leader of Hadassah including items pertaining to Israel. Mr. Evans's mayoral correspondence is divided into a general file and a subject file. In pictures and personal correspondence, the Nachamson family is often represented. One early clipping from a Fayetteville, N.C. newspaper, tells of Mr. Evans's sister being refused teaching positions because of her Jewish faith. Eli Evans is a correspondent and writer, led the establishment of the National Jewish Archives of Broadcasting, and was on the staff of the Carnegie Foundation that helped launch "Sesame Street." He was president of the UNC student body and a number of items in the collection concern his presidency.
Also included is an address of Eli Evans presented during the conference on Southern-Jewish history in 1976, Eli Evans's vita, his unpublished diary of the Kissinger shuttle, and a large number of his writings, many concerning U.S. politics, minorities, and Jews in the South. There is a reprint of a chapter from his book, The Provincials, and reports from the Charles H. Revson Foundation, of which he is president. Also included are materials concerning Eli's brother Robert, a correspondent with CBS, who continued on as a television executive. Their uncle, Monroe Evans, was mayor of Fayetteville, NC, and his service is documented in several of the collection's scrapbooks.
One entire scrapbook is devoted to the writings of Mildred and Madeline Evans, Monroe's wife and daughter.
The audiovisual series contains a 16mm film copy of a 1957 episode of Edward R. Murrow's "See It Now," with which Robert Evans was involved, and a 16mm film copy of Governor Terry Sanford's November 1964 appearance on WUNC-TV, in which he reflects on his governorship and the current political scene. Several audio recordings capture Sara Evans addressing the Seaboard Regional Conference of Hadassah in 1982. Eli N. Evans's appearance on Richard D. Heffner's The Open Mind is documented.
Antisemitism; Jews in the Southern States; Photographs; Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Israel; Department stores -- North Carolina; Department stores; United States -- Politics and government; Display of merchandise; Evans, Sara Nachamson, 1905-1986; Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America; Evans, Monroe; Evans, Robert; Nachamson family; University of North Carolina -- Alumni; Evans, Eli N.; Evans, Emanuel J.; Charles H. Revson Foundation
- Evans Family Series
  - Addresses and Writings, 1946-1977, undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Alumni Annual Giving (Box 1)
  - The American Israel Honorarium, Vol. 2 (Box 24)
  - American Israel Public Affairs Committee, 1976-1982 (Box 24)
  - Artifacts (Box 29)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes 2 gavels, 2 Hadassah medals, and Bar Mitzvah prayerbooks for both Eli and Robert.
  - Beth El Synagogue history by Sara Evans, with related correspondence (Box 25)
  - Biographical information, 1953-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Family biographies, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Business correspondence, 1937-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Civic Honor Award of the Durham Chamber of Commerce, Evans, E. J. (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1926-1951 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1952-1977, undated, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Committee of One Hundred (Chamber of Commerce) (Box 2)
  - Congratulations (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1976, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1977, undated (Box 4)
  - Evans, E. J. "Father of the Year," 1965 (Box 4)
  - Evans, Sara, Obituaries, 1986 (Box 4)
  - E. J. and Sara's 50th wedding anniversary scrapbook (Box 30)
    Scrapbook of well-wishes and celebrations of their anniversary.
  - Duke archives donation, 1977 (Box 24)
  - Durham Federation of Jewish Charities (Box 4)
  - Family honors and awards, oversize, 1960s-1990s (Box 28)
  - Hadassah, 4 folders
    - Miscellaneous Hadassah materials, 1954-1977 and undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1934-1980s (Box 25)
    - Durham Board Meeting notes, 1920s-1970s, 5 folders (Box 25)
    - Durham chapter membership list, oversize (Box 28)
    - Sara Evans' miscellaneous correspondence and documents, 1980s (Box 25)
    - Walter Eytan visit to Duke, 1982 (Box 25)
    - Zionist Affairs regional documents, 1971-1978 and undated (Box 25)
    - Correspondence with local members, 1978-1983 and undated (Box 25)
    - Durham Chapter, 1979-1984 and undated (Box 25)
    - Southern Seaboard Region correspondence, etc., 1964-1983, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Southern Seaboard Regional Conference, 1984 (Box 25)
    - Durham Federation, 1983 (Box 25)
    - Ya'al, 1954-1982 (Box 25)
    - Correspondence with national office, 1976-1984, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 24)
  - Judaic Studies Program
    - Miscellaneous materials, Duke University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1972-1977, undated (Box 5)
    - Press release and publicity, 1971-1977 (Box 24)
    - Study programs, correspondence, 1970s (Box 24)
    - Finances, 1972-1973 (Box 24)
    - Filled pledges, 1970s (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 24)
    - Dedications of Judaic Studies Program, 1974 (Box 24)
    - Dedication of Evans Judaic Hall, 1980 (Box 24)
    - Scrapbook (disbound) from dedication of Evans Judaic Hall, 1980 (Box 24)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1985, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Student oral history project with Beth-El Synagogue, undated (Box 24)
  - Miscellany, 1929-1976, undated (Box 5)
  - NC Association for Jewish Women, 1977 (Box 24)
  - Preferred Stock Certificates (4 vols.) (Box 6)
  - President of the Student Body at the University of North Carolina, Evans, Eli N. (Box 7)
  - Printed material, 1928-1977, undated (Box 7)
  - Printed material, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Synagogue Center/Percival Goodman (Box 7)
  - Suspense file, 1949-1962 (Box 7)
  - United Fund (Box 7)
  - United Jewish Appeal, 1957-1966 (Box 7)
  - University of North Carolina (Box 7)
  - Vistas, Inc.: President's file, 1960-1971, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Watts Hospital (Box 8)
  - Watts Hospital Bond Speakers (Box 8)
  - Oversize materials (Box Sec. A OV5)
  - Oversize publications profiling the Evans family, 1950s-1960s (Box 28)
  - Photographs
    - E. J. Evans, 1917-1973, undated (Box 5)
    - E. J. Evans, 1920s-1980s and undated (Box 24)
    - E. J. Evans as Mayor of Durham, 1951-1966 and undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Sara N. Evans, 1928-1972, undated (Box 5)
    - Sara Evans, undated (Box 24)
    - Robert M. and Eli N. Evans, 1950-1974, undated (Box 5)
    - Robert Evans, 1950s-1960s (Box 24)
    - Eli Evans, 1980s (Box 24)
    - Eli Evans' album from his service on the USS Saint Paul, 1959 (Box 30)
      Includes snapshots with captions documenting his Navy tour through Japan.
    - Evans Family, 1940-1976, undated (Box 5)
    - Evans Family, 1940s-1990s (Box 24)
    - E. J. and Sara's 50th wedding anniversary album, 1978 (Box 28)
      Disbound scrapbook album of photographs celebrating their anniversary.
    - Israel, 1976 (slides) (Box 24)
    - Nachamson family, 1901-1970, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellany, 1934-1953 (Box 6)
    - Miscellany, 1953-1977, undated (Box 6)
    - Durham house, 1021 Dacian Ave. (Box 24)
    - Oversize photographs of Robert and Eli (Box 28)
- E. J. "Mutt" Evans Series
  - Mayor's Office
    - Airport, 1952-1961 (Box 9)
    - Appointment for committees, etc. (Box 9)
    - Annual Report (Box 9)
    - Aull, Jr., George H. (City Manager, Durham, N.C.) (Box 9)
    - Centennial (Box 9)
    - Change and improvements, 1953-1961 (Box 9)
    - Complaints and suggestions from individuals (Box 9)
    - "Congratulations for Mayor," 1951, Mar-1961, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence (general), 1951-1953, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (general), 1954-1963, undated, 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Correspondence (personal) 1951-1963, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - "Fluoride" (Box 12)
    - Housing Authority (Box 12)
    - Human Relations Committee (Box 12)
    - Lerner, Connie: Miss North Carolina, 1971 (Box 12)
    - Long Range Planning Committee (Chamber of Commerce) (Box 12)
    - Mayor's campaigns, 1951-1963, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Mayor's campaign posters, 1950s-1960s (Box 28)
    - N.C. League of Municipalities, 1951-1961, undated (Box 13)
    - Office of Emergency Planning (Civil Defense Advisory Council) (Box 13)
    - Radio/Television Stations (Box 13)
    - Special Invitations To and From the Mayor, 1958-1950 (Box 13)
    - Speech material (Box 13)
    - "Thank You" letters (Box 13)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 13)
  - General Files, 1920s-1990s
    - Memorial book and memorials, 1997-1998 (Box 27)
    - Honors and awards (Box 27)
      Includes color reproduction photocopies of original plaques.
    - Home Security salute by Evans, 1959 (Box 27)
    - Tau Epsilon Phi Fraternity, 1924-1980s (Box 27)
    - UNC materials, 1920s (Box 27)
    - Clippings (Box 27)
    - Personal correspondence, 1974-1990 (Box 27)
    - City Hall mayor portrait, 1983 (Box 27)
    - Correspondence with VIPs (Senators, etc.), 1970s-1980s (Box 27)
- Sara Evans Series
  - Personal correspondence re: family set-up/reunions, 1960s-1980s (Box 26)
    "Family set-up" refers to the United Nachamsons' financial accounts.
  - Writings on Russian Jewry, 1966 (Box 26)
  - Research, correspondence from Hadassah trip to Russia, 1960 and 1966 (Box 26)
  - Personal correspondence, 1950s-1986, 7 folders (Box 26)
  - Speeches, 1956-1979 (Box 26)
  - Clippings (Box 26)
  - Condolences upon Sara's death, 1986 (Box 26)
  - Memorials/obituaries, 1986 (Box 26)
  - Memorial trees (Box 26)
  - Clippings re: Sara Evans' death and memorial, 1986 (Box 26)
- Robert M. Evans Series
  - Resumes/biography/CVs (Box 27)
  - Personal correspondence, 1950s (Box 27)
  - UNC materials (Box 27)
  - Omar Bradley visit to UNC, 1951 (Box 27)
  - Mark Clark visit to UNC, 1951 (Box 27)
  - Carolina Forum correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 27)
  - Dept. of Navy service, 1952 (Box 27)
  - Rhodes Scholar application, 1954 (Box 27)
  - Writings about Israel, 1954-1955 (Box 27)
  - Afghanistan Expedition clippings, materials, 1956, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - "Japan: Friend or Foe" draft, undated (Box 27)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Speaking engagements (Box 27)
  - Writings re: Berlin, 1961-1962 (Box 27)
  - U.S. Information Agency press releases, 1961-1963, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - E.R. Murrow remarks, statements, speeches, 1961-1963, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 27)
  - Essay honoring Sara Evans, 1989 (Box 27)
- Eli N. Evans Series
  - Addresses and Writings of Eli N. Evans (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 27)
  - Foreword for "A Proud History" (Box 27)
  - WNET: Civilization and the Jews (Box 27)
  - Terry Sanford materials (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous documents (Box 27)
  - Diary of the Kissinger Shuttle, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Addresses and writings of others (Box 14)
  - Biography (Box 14)
  - Charles H. Revson Foundation, 1978-1986 (Box 14)
  - Charles H. Revson Foundation public broadcasting materials (Box 27)
  - Pictures (Box 14)
  - The Provincials: A Personal History of Jews in the South by Eli N. Evans (Box 14)
  - The Provincials: press, reviews, etc., 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Resume/biography/CVs (Box 27)
  - UNC Student President election, 1957 (Box 27)
  - Judah P. Benjamin: reviews, press, etc. (Box 27)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Publicity for published works, oversize (Box 28)
- Scrapbook Series
  - Evans Family, Pictures, ca. 1922-1947 (Box 15)
  - Eli N. Evans, Pictures, High School and UNC (Box 15)
  - Evans Family, "Special Events," 1928-1977 (Box 16)
  - Sara N. Evans, "This is My Life," 1954-1962 (Box 16)
  - E. J. Evans, 1936-1976 (Box 17)
  - Robert M. Evans, 1920-1977 (Box 17)
  - Sara N. Evans, "Eight Sisters in Israel, November - December 1968" (Box 17)
  - Eli N. Evans, Student Body President, UNC, 1957-1958 (Box 18)
  - E. J. Evans, "Retiring Mayor, Durham, NC," 1963 (Box 18)
  - Evans Family, "Publicity," 1928-1955 (Box 18)
  - Evans Family, Pictures, 1948-1976 (Box 19)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral September 1966-March 1967" (Box 19)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral July 1965-September 1966" (Box 20)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "Mayoral March 1965-June 1965" (Box 20)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "March 1967-April 1969" (Box 21)
  - Monroe E. Evans, 1921-1959 (Box 22)
  - Monroe E. Evans, 1969 (Box 23)
  - Monroe E. Evans, "United Service Fund, 1957-1972" (Box 23)
  - Madeline and Mildred Evans, "Writings," 1958-1963 (Box 23)
- Audiovisual materials, 1964-2005; 1
  - See It Now: England After Suez, part 1, 1957-03-03; 1
    - Original 16mm film, sd., b&w (Box 33, Film-reel RL00369-F16-0001)
  - See It Now: England After Suez, part 2, 1957-03-03; 2
    - Original 16mm film, sd., b&w (Box 33, Film-reel RL00369-F16-0002)
  - Palm Beach, 1964-10-29; 3
    - Original 1/4-inch (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0003)
  - Recorded speech of Mrs. E.J. Evans, at King's Bay Yacht Club, Miami, Florida, 1964-11-02; 4
    - Original 1/4-inch (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0002)
  - Governor Sanford, WUNC-TV, 1964-11-10; 5
    - Original 16mm film, sd., b&w (Box 34, Film-reel RL00369-F16-0003)
  - Chamber Distinguished Service Award Presentation, Dr. Rankin and Mr. E.J. Evans, 1965-01-19; 6
    - Original 1/4-inch (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0001)
  - Dedication of Judaic Hall and dinner speeches, 1980-04-14; 7
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0006)
  - Seaboard Regional Conference, Speaker Sara Evans, years 1920 to 1950, 1982-05-02; 8
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0004)
  - Sara speaks at Seaboard Regional Conference, at evening session, 1982-05-02; 9
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0005)
  - Sara speaks at Seaboard Regional Conference, night session, 1982-05-03; 10
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0001)
  - Sara speaks, 1982-05-03; 11
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0002)
  - Sara speaks at Hadassah Seaboard Region; presentation of 1982 Myrtle Wreath Award to Mutt, Hadassah Regional Conf., 1982-05-03; 12
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0003)
  - The Open Mind: On Being "The Other", Host: Richard D. Heffner, Guest: Eli N. Evans, 2005-05-11; 13
    - Original VHS (Box 32, Video-cassette RL00369-VHS-0001)
  - The Open Mind: On Being "The Other", Host: Richard D. Heffner, Guest: Eli N. Evans, 2005-05-11; 14
    - Original DVD (Box 32, Video-disc RL00369-DVD-0001)
  - The Open Mind: On Being "The Other", Host: Richard D. Heffner, Guest: Eli N. Evans, 2005-05-11; 15
    - Original DVD (Box 32, Video-disc RL00369-DVD-0002)
  - untitled, undated; 16
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0004)
  - Perry Como, undated; 17
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0005)
  - untitled, undated; 18
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0006)
  - untitled, undated; 19
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0007)
  - untitled, undated; 20
    - Original 1/4-inch open reel audio tape (Box 32, Audio-reel RL00369-RR-0008)
  - Introduction, undated; 21
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0007)
  - untitled, undated; 22
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0008)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 23
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0009)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 24
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0010)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 25
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0011)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 26
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0012)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 27
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0013)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 28
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0014)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 29
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0015)
  - untitled - possibly backup copy of other audiocassette in collection (made by Duke), undated; 30
    - Original audiocassette (Box 32, Audio-cassette RL00369-CS-0016)